When I think about dreams,
عندما أفكر بالأحلام،
like many of you,
كالكثير منكم،
I think about this picture.
أفكر بهذه الصورة.
I was eight when I watched Neil Armstrong
كنت في الثامنة عندما رأيت "نيل ارمسترونغ"
step off the Lunar Module onto the surface of the Moon.
يترجل من المركبة القمرية إلى سطح القمر.
I had never seen anything like it before,
لم أر مثيلاً لهذا من قبل،
and I've never seen anything like it since.
و لم أر مثيلاً لهذا منذ ذلك الحين.
We got to the Moon for one simple reason:
بلغنا القمر لسبب بسيط واحد:
John Kennedy committed us to a deadline.
ألزمنا "جون كينيدي" بموعد نهائي.
And in the absence of that deadline,
و بدون ذلك الميعاد النهائي،
we would still be dreaming about it.
لكُنا مازلنا نحلم به الآن.
Leonard Bernstein said two things are necessary for great achievement:
قال "لينورد بيرنستين" : هناك شيئان ضروريان للإنجازات العظيمة
a plan and not quite enough time.
خطة ووقت غير كافي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Deadlines and commitments
المواعيد النهائية والإلتزامات
are the great and fading lessons of Apollo.
هي الدروس العظيمة والمتلاشية لأبولو (بعثة فضائية للقمر).
And they are what give the word "moonshot" its meaning.
و هي التي تمنح كلمة " المجازفة " معناها.
And our world is in desperate need of political leaders
و عالمنا بحاجة ماسة إلى قادة سياسيين
willing to set bold deadlines
قادرين على وضع حدود زمنية جريئة
for the achievement of daring dreams on the scale of Apollo again.
لإنجاز أحلامنا الجريئة من مستوى أبولو من جديد.
When I think about dreams,
عندما أفكر بالأحلام،
I think about the drag queens of LA and Stonewall
أفكر بالرجال المُتَقمصين لأدوار النساء في لوس أنجلوس وستونوول
and millions of other people risking everything
وملايين من الناس الآخرين الذين يجازفون بكل شئ
to come out when that was really dangerous,
للظهور في وقت كان من الخطر جدا الظهور فيه،
and of this picture of the White House lit up in rainbow colors,
وهذه الصورة للبيت الأبيض مُضاءا بألوان قوس قزح،
yes --
نعم -
(Applause) --
(تصفيق) -
celebrating America's gay and lesbian citizens' right to marry.
إحتفالاً بحق المثليين والمثليات الأمريكيين في الزواج.
It is a picture that in my wildest dreams I could never have imagined
صورة لم أكن لأتخيلها أبدا في أشد أحلامي جرأة
when I was 18
عندما كنت في الثامنة عشر
and figuring out that I was gay
وأدركت أني كنت مِثليا
and feeling estranged from my country
وشعرت بالغربة في بلدي
and my dreams because of it.
وفي أحلامي بسبب ذلك.
I think about this picture of my family
أفكر في هذه الصورة لعائلتي
that I never dreamed I could ever have --
التي لم أتخيل أبدا أن يكون لدي مثلها -
(Applause) --
(تصفيق) -
and of our children holding this headline
وفي أطفالنا الذي يحملون تلك الشعارات
I never dreamed could ever be printed about the Supreme Court ruling.
عن حكم المحكمة العليا الذي لم أتخيل أبدا أن يكون.
We need more of the courage of drag queens and astronauts.
نحتاج لمزيد من شجاعة الممثلين المرتدين لأزياء النساء ورواد الفضاء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But I want to talk about the need for us to dream
لكني أود الحديث عن حاجتنا للحُلم
in more than one dimension,
في أكثر من بُعد،
because there was something about Apollo that I didn't know when I was 8,
لأن هنالك شيئ ما بخصوص أبولو لم أعرفه عندما كنت في الثامنة من عمري،
and something about organizing that the rainbow colors over.
وشيئا عن ترتيب ألوان قوس قزح.
Of the 30 astronauts in the original Mercury, Gemini and Apollo programs,
من بين 30 رائد فضاء في برامج الفضاء (ميركري)، (جيميني) و(أبولو)،
only seven marriages survived.
سبعة فقط هم من كانت زيجاتهم مستقرة.
Those iconic images of the astronauts bouncing on the Moon
هذه الصور الأيقونية لرواد الفضاء يتقافزون على سطح القمر
obscure the alcoholism and depression on Earth.
بينما يعانون من إدمان الكحول والإكتئاب على الأرض.
Thomas Merton, the Trappist monk,
(توماس ميرتون) الراهب،
asked during the time of Apollo,
سأل خلال وقت أبولو،
"What can we gain by sailing to the moon
"ماذا سنكسب من رحلتنا إلى القمر
if we are not able to cross the abyss that separates us from ourselves?"
مادمنا لا نستطيع تخطي الهاوية التي تفصِلنا عن أنفِسِنا؟"
And what can we gain by the right to marry
ماذا سنكسب بمنح حق الزواج
if we are not able to cross the acrimony
مادمنا غير قادرين على تخطي حدة الطِباع
and emotional distance that so often separates us from our love?
والمسافات العاطفية التي تفصلنا غالبا عمن نحب؟
And not just in marriage.
ليس فقط في الزواج.
I have seen the most hurtful, destructive,
لقد رأيت أشد الآلام تدميرا،
tragic infighting in LGBT and AIDS
مأساوية في محاربة المثليين والإيدز
and breast cancer and non-profit activism,
وسرطان الثدي والأنشطة التطوعية،
all in the name of love.
كل ذلك باسْم الحب.
Thomas Merton also wrote about wars among saints
(توماس ميرتون) كتب أيضاً عن الإقتتال بين القديسيين
and that "there is a pervasive form of contemporary violence
وعن وجود "إنتشار للعنف المُعاصِر
to which the idealist most easily succumbs:
الذي يُخضِع دُعاة المثالية بكل سهولة:
activism and overwork.
النشاط والإرهاق.
The frenzy of our activism neutralizes our work for peace.
جنون نشاطنا يعادل عملنا من أجل السلام.
It destroys our own inner capacity for peace."
إنه يدمر طاقة تَحَمُلْنا للحفاظ على السلام."
Too often our dreams become these compartmentalized fixations
في الأعم الأغلب تصبح أحلامنا مُجَزَئَة ومُعَلَقة
on some future
بوقت ما في المستقبل
that destroy our ability to be present for our lives right now.
وهذا يدمر قدرتنا على أن نعيش حياتنا في اللحظة الحاضرة.
Our dreams of a better life for some future humanity
أحلامنا في الوصول لحياة أفضل في مستقبلنا البشري
or some other humanity in another country
أو مُستَقبَل بشرية أخرى في دولة أخرى
alienate us from the beautiful human beings sitting next to us
تجعلنا ننصرف عن الحياة البشرية الجميلة الموجودة على مقربة منا
at this very moment.
في كل لحظة.
Well, that's just the price of progress, we say.
حسنا، هذه هي ضريبة التَقَدم، كما نقول.
You can go to the Moon
تستطيع أن تذهب إلى القمر
or you can have stability in your family life.
أو تحافظ على تماسُك حياتك العائلية.
And we can't conceive of dreaming in both dimensions at the same time.
ولا يمكننا تصور حياة تجمع بين الإثنين في ذات الوقت.
And we don't set the bar much higher than stability
ونحن لا نرقى بأهدافنا ومن ثَمَ نكتفي بالإستقرار فحسب
when it comes to our emotional life.
عندما يتعلق الأمر بحياتنا العاطفية.
Which is why our technology for talking to one another
ولهذا فالتكنولوجيا صُمِمَت بحيث نتحدث لبعضنا البعض
has gone vertical,
بشكل مُتَزايد،
our ability to listen and understand one another
قدرتنا على الإستماع وفهم أحدنا الآخر
has gone nowhere.
قد تلاشت.
Our access to information is through the roof,
وصولنا للمعلومات سهل للغاية،
our access to joy, grounded.
ووصولنا للسعادة، في أدنى مستوياته.
But this idea, that our present and our future are mutually exclusive,
لكن فكرة أن حاضرنا ومستقبلنا متضادان،
that to fulfill our potential for doing we have to surrender
أي إذا أردنا إنجاز شيء لمستقبلنا، فعلينا أن نتنازل
our profound potential for being,
عن حاجتنا لأن نحيا حاضرنا،
that the number of transistors on a circuit can be doubled and doubled,
أعداد الترانزستور في الدائرة الكهربائية تتضاعف وتتضاعف،
but our capacity for compassion and humanity and serenity and love
لكن طاقة إستيعابنا للشفقة والإنسانية والصفاء والحب
is somehow limited
بطريقة ما محدودة
is a false and suffocating choice.
هذا إختيار خاطئ وخانِقْ.
Now, I'm not suggesting
الآن، أنا لا أقترح
simply the uninspiring idea of more work-life balance.
ببساطة تلك الفكرة غير المُلهِمة عن المزيد من التوازن بين العمل والحياة.
What good is it for me to spend more time with my kids at home
فما الجيد في قضاء وقت أطول مع أطفالي في البيت
if my mind is always somewhere else while I'm doing it?
إذا كان عقلي دائما في مكان آخر بينما أنا بينهم؟
I'm not even talking about mindfulness.
أنا لا أتحدث حتى عن انشغال العقل.
Mindfulness is all of a sudden becoming a tool for improving productivity.
أصبح انشغال العقل وبشكل مُفاجئ أداة لتحسين الإنتاجية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Right?
صحيح؟
I'm talking about dreaming
أنا أتحدث عن الحُلْم
as boldly in the dimension of our being
أن نَحْلُم بجرأة فيما يتعلق بذواتنا
as we do about industry and technology.
كما هي أحلامنا جريئة تجاه الصناعة والتكنولوجيا.
I'm talking about an audacious authenticity
أنا أتحدث عن الأصالة الجريئة
that allows us to cry with one another,
التي تسمح لنا أن نبكي سويا،
a heroic humility that allows us to remove our masks and be real.
في تواضع بُطُولي يسمح لنا أن ننزع عنا الأقنعة ونكون أنفُسَنا.
It is our inability to be with one another,
إن عدم قدرتنا على أن نكون سويا،
our fear of crying with one another, that gives rise to so many
وخوفنا من أن نبكي أمام أحدنا الآخر، هي ما أدى لظهور العديد
of the problems we are frantically trying to solve in the first place,
من المشاكل التي نحاول حلها بشكل محموم في المقام الأول،
from Congressional gridlock to economic inhumanity.
بداية من جلسات الكونجرس الفاشلة وصولاً إلى الإقتصاد الوَحشي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I'm talking about what Jonas Salk called an Epoch B,
أنا أتحدث عما سماه (جوناس سالك) الـ "عصر ب"،
a new epoch in which we become as excited about and curious about
عصر جديد نصبح فيه متحمسين ومُتَطَلِعين
and scientific about the development of our humanity
وعِلميين فيما يتعلق بتطور إنسانيتنا
as we are about the development of our technology.
بنفس الطريقة التي نحن عليها تجاه التكنولوجيا.
We should not shrink from this opportunity
لا ينبغي أن نُقَلِل من هذه الفرضية
simply because we don't really understand it.
فقط لأننا لا نفهمها.
There was a time when we didn't understand space.
فقد كان هناك وقت لم نفهم فيه الفضاء.
Or because we're more used to technology and activism.
أو لإننا معتادين أكثر على التكنولوجيا والنشاط.
That is the very definition of being stuck in a comfort zone.
هذا هو تحديدا ما يعنيه أن تعْلَقْ في روتينك المُرِيح.
We are now very comfortable imagining unimaginable technological achievement.
نحن الآن مرتاحين للغاية في تخيلنا للإنجازات التكنولوجية الخيالية.
In 2016, it is the dimension of our being itself
سنة 2016، هي البُعْد الذي يُمِكن لذواتنا
that cries out for its fair share of our imagination.
أن تُطالِب فيه لنفسها بمُشَاركَة عادلة لأحلامنا.
Now, we're all here to dream,
الآن، نحن هنا جميعا لكي نَحْلُم،
but maybe if we're honest about it,
لكن لوأننا صادقين مع أنفسنا،
each of us chasing our own dream.
لقٌلْنا أن كل منا يسعى لحلمه الخاص به.
You know, looking at the name tags to see who can help me with my dream,
كما تعلم، أنت تبحث بين الأسماء لعلك تجد من قد يساعدك في تحقيق حُلْمِك،
sometimes looking right through one another's humanity.
أحيانا تبحث في إنسانية الآخر.
I can't be bothered with you right now. I have an idea for saving the world.
أنا لست مصدر إزعاج لكم الآن. فأنا لدي فكرة تُنقِذ البشرية.
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Years ago, once upon a time, I had this beautiful company
منذ سنوات مضت، في وقت ما، كانت لدي شركة جميلة
that created these long journeys for heroic civic engagement.
حيث قُمْنا بعمل رحلات طويلة من أجل بطولات ملحمية مدنية.
And we had this mantra:
وكانت لدينا تعويذة:
"Human. Kind. Be Both."
" الإنسان. الطيبة. معا."
And we encouraged people to experiment outrageously with kindness.
وشجعنا الناس لتجربة مليئة بالطيبة.
Like, "Go help everybody set up their tents."
مثل، "اذهب ساعد الآخرين في نَصْب خيامِهِم."
And there were a lot of tents.
وكان هناك الكثير من الخيام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Go buy everybody Popsicles."
"اذهب واشترِ للجميع مصاصات."
"Go help people fix their flat tires
"ساعد الناس في ملء الإطارات الفارغة
even though you know the dinner line is going to get longer."
حتي لو كنت تعلم أنك ستتأخر على طابور العشاء."
And people really took us up on this,
والناس أخذوا هذا الكلام على محمل الجد،
so much so that if you got a flat tire on the AIDS ride,
ونفذوه بحذافيره لدرجة أن إطارك لو فَرغ في "جولة الإيدز"،
you had trouble fixing it, because there were so many people there asking you
ستكون لديك مشكلة في إصلاحه، لأن الجميع سيكونون هناك يسألونك
if you needed help.
إن كنت تحتاج للمساعدة.
For a few days, for tens of thousands of people,
لأيام قلائل، ومع عشرات الآلاف من الناس،
we created these worlds
صنعنا هذا العالم
that everybody said were the way they wish the world could always be.
الذي يحيا فيه الجميع كما يريد.
What if we experimented with creating that kind of world
ماذا لو أننا جربنا أن نصنع هذا العالم
these next few days?
في الأيام القليلة القادمة؟
And instead of going up to someone and asking them, "What do you do?"
وبدلاً من ذهابنا لأحدهم لنسأله "ما هو عملك؟"
ask them, "So what are your dreams?"
نسأله، "ما هي أحلامك؟"
or "What are your broken dreams?"
أو "ما هي أحلامك التي لم تتحقق؟"
You know, "TED." Tend to Each other's Dreams.
تعرفون، لنجعل معنى "TED" "لنقترب من أحلام بعضنا البعض."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Maybe it's "I want to stay sober"
ربما هي "أود أن أحافظ على رصانتي"
or "I want to build a tree house with my kid."
أو "أود أبني بيت على الشجرة لأطفالي."
You know, instead of going up to the person everybody wants to meet,
تعلمون، بدلاً من ذهابنا لشخص يتمنى الجميع أن يقابله،
go up to the person who is all alone
فلنذهب لذلك الوحيد دائما
and ask them if they want to grab a cup of coffee.
ولنسأله إن كان يريد كوبا من القهوة.
I think what we fear most
أعتقد أن أكثر ما يخيفنا
is that we will be denied the opportunity to fulfill our true potential,
هو أن نُضَيع فرصتنا في حياة وافِية تتناسب مع إمكانياتنا،
that we are born to dream
تلك الحياة التي ولدنا لنَحْلُم بها
and we might die without ever having the chance.
ونخشى أن نموت دون أن تكون لدينا الفرصة أن نحياها.
Imagine living in a world
تخيل حياتك في عالم
where we simply recognize that deep, existential fear in one another
حيث يمكننا بكل بساطة أن نتعرف على ذلك الخوف العميق الموجود فينا
and love one another boldly because we know
ويحب أحدنا الأخر بقوة لأننا نعلم
that to be human is to live with that fear.
أن كونك إنسان يقتَضي أن تعيش مع هذا الخوف.
It's time for us to dream in multiple dimensions simultaneously,
حان الوقت لنحلم في أبعاد متعددة في نفس الوقت،
and somewhere that transcends all of the wondrous things
وفي أماكن تتجاوز كل العجائب
we can and will and must do
التي نستطيع ويتوجب علينا فعلها
lies the domain of all the unbelievable things we could be.
أن نصنع مجالاً لكل الأشياء التي بإستطاعتنا فعلها.
It's time we set foot into that dimension
حان الوقت لنخطو في ذلك البُعد
and came out about the fact that we have dreams there, too.
ونعترف بحقيقة أن لنا أحلاما فيه، كذلك.
If the Moon could dream,
لو كان بإمكان القمر أن يحلم،
I think that would be its dream for us.
فأنا أعتقد أن هذا هو ما سيريده لأجلنا.
It's an honor to be with you.
شَرِفٌ لي أن أكون بينكم.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)